Welcome to the seminar on people
computers and design. Um
I will do a brief introduction today. We
started a touch late. Um I guess Will
Wright who's our speaker today is one of
these people who makes me uncomfortably
aware of the generation gap. And that's
not because of him. He's sort of in
between my generation the next one. But
because the things that he's done uh in
particular, he was the inventor of Sim
City and a whole series of innovative uh
programs and games since then are things
which I discovered as a computer science
professor learning about interface
design. And when I look out into a
classroom full of students nowadays,
they're people who discovered it the way
that I discovered model cars, right?
That is they grew up with it. uh that
the kind of tools and and games and
whatever you want to call them he's
producing have really been a major part
of life with computers, what it means to
be computers and use computers for the
generation that's just now uh appearing
in college. uh and my own intuition,
which I of course can't validate since
I'm in the wrong generation, but is that
that's going to lead over time to a real
shift in the way not just the people
think about games, but people think
about computers and computing in
general. Um, and today he's going to be
talking about his experience and his
ideas along those lines.
Thank you, Terry. Um,
yeah, I guess I'm kind of from that in
between generation. uh spent a lot of
time building models when I was a kid.
Way too much time building models when I
was a kid. Um and I really was
fascinated by the idea of these kind of
micro systems, models, micro worlds,
whatever. Uh you got there now and you
can't find models the way they used to
be. Used to be you could find plastic
models, wooden models all over the
place. And that's what kids did,
especially boys. um whereas girls would
play with the dolls which was a
different kind of modeling or a social
system model. Uh that whole industry
seems to have been displaced recently by
the video game industry which to me is
kind of sad in a way because on the
modeling front there was so much
creativity involved. You would spend so
much time and there were just infinite
levels of progression. I started out
with these kind of plastic models you'd
glue together. Then I kind of got into
the wooden ones, the pre-formed wooden
ones where you'd glue them together and
build these airplanes and put the paper
over it. And then eventually started
building my own just out of scratch
wood. And it was really interesting to
me because you could get such a good
sense of the structural definition of a
system with these models. So when I got
a computer in my early 20s, a friend of
mine talked me into buying one. I very
quickly realized how cool the computer
was as a modeling tool.
the uh computer all of a sudden allows
you to start modeling process in
addition to just structure. So uh my
definitions here are kind of loose and
freewheeling but uh like a tree the
structure might be the leaves and the
branches and whatnot. Process might be
combustion you know structural change in
the tree. So for the first time with a
computer I had a tool that I could start
modeling process with. And as a model
builder, I just went hog wild, taught
myself to program, and kind of got into
the games industry. Um, this is about 15
years ago now. I was supposed to talk
here today about interface design, and
I'm going to try to, but really I'm
going to touch on three major areas. I
think I'm going to talk on simulation
design, game design, and interface
design. Because those three to me are
very tightly linked. I can't just design
the interface after the game's done or
design the game in isolation from the
interface. Um, each one of these
supports the other and a lot of times
there'll be a game I want to do, but I
can't design the interface to support it
or the simulation underneath that it
needs to have. So, to me, these three
kind of go in this dynamic process and
design together. So, um, I'll be talking
about all three today. I'm going to be
showing you some of our older games kind
of in chronological order and going
through some of the issues we were
thinking about, why we did things the
way we did. Um, and then lessons learned
after it was out there and hundreds of
thousands of people were complaining
about it and telling us how bad a job we
did. Um, we get some more perspective
after time and then, you know, each one
after that we would try to address the
problems and usually we'd overshoot or
we'd go off in a totally different
direction and invent new problems for
the users. Uh on the simulation side,
most of the games we do are about real
world systems. Um so the simulation in a
sense is leading the charge on the
educational front. We pick a system that
we want to educate the user about and
then we look at the simulation design
and how much of the system do we want to
wrap the user's mind around. Um there
are a lot of issues there in terms of
how much of a simulation do we put in?
How high is the fidelity of the
situation? When does it match reality
versus users expectations? Um on the
game design, a lot of times we will
decide to make the simulation match
users expectations rather than reality.
Uh in certain cases, if otherwise it
would destroy the gameplay. Um on the
game design, games are really all about
problem solving, constraints,
challenges. So simulation is more about
modeling the real world. So the
simulation is where the problem is
usually embedded. We will build a
simulation so that the problems come up.
Uh as far as the simulation is
concerned, they're not problems. It's
just data going through some uh
algorithms. It's the game design that
basically points you toward a goal. So
the game design is actually going to
tell you what is a problem in the
simulation, what constraints the user
has to deal with that problem, and those
constraints are typically where the
gameplay is going to come from. Uh the
interface has to support both of these
processes. Uh you have to visualize the
simulation. There are a lot of issues
with how much of the simulation do we
make explicit to the user. Sometimes we
don't want to show every last detail of
the simulation to the user. Uh we want
to sometimes prop up this illusion of
reality and that's one of these issues
where the game design is in opposition
to the simulation design. Sometimes as
an educator a lot of people
would rather see simulations that were
very explicit in the way they modeled or
in uh what the user sees of the modeling
process. In other words, they want the
users to know exactly how Sim City is
calculating the traffic rate or why
crime appears, what the algorithm for
crime is. On a game design front, that's
not always desirable. If you make the
system too explicit, a, you destroy that
illusion of reality, and b, you take
away some of the challenge of the
problem solving. One of the things that
we think about uh on the education front
is that when we're designing a model,
we're not necessarily designing a
computer model. our real end product is
the uh mental model in the player's
head. We're trying to give them maybe a
more robust model of the way a city
works or a planet works or whatever. The
computer model really is just an
incremental step in that direction. It's
like a compiler for the middle model. So
uh
the actions that the user is allowed to
do in the interface basically define how
you can deal with the problems and these
are the constraints. Most of the uh
interfaces I'm going to show you
conceptually can be kind of split into
the data output you know problem
identification side and the data input
problem solving side where the tools are
applied and the user actually has input
to the model.
the uh one of the paradigms we've tried
to use in designing these simulations is
to think of them a little bit more as
toys rather than games. That is to leave
them a little more open-ended. They're
not necessarily as goal- directed as
most games would be. Most games you have
a very single-minded goal. You solve
that, you win. Uh the kind of
simulations we've been moving towards
really are a little more open-ended
where in a lot of cases the user is
deciding what the goal is before they
play. when they play Sim City for
instance, we don't necessarily tell them
you have to get the biggest city you can
or you have to make your residents as
happy as can be. People will actually
take it and play different ways. They'll
basically identify, they'll think of,
well, what's my goal today or what kind
of city do I want to build? I want to
build a city that has the happiest
possible residence and then they'll try
to meet that goal. So, it's a little
more open-ended the way a ball can be
used for different games. The user
decides what the goal is. You know, if I
kick the ball through the goal, then I
win. Uh that's the way I think of these
kind of as software toys rather than
games. Um
there was a really cool uh short story
written by Stannis Lim called the
Seventh Sally
and he describes this he's got these
robot cultures and they go around doing
these things and uh one of the robots
who was an inventor Tur came across this
asteroid where there was this deposed
dictator all by himself and he was
really sad because he didn't have a
kingdom to rule and so Turl invented
this magical invention for him and it
was a box with a whole kingdom inside
that he could rule and enslave and do
bad things to with little knobs to
control them. He never got real explicit
about what the interface was.
Really fancy knobs.
Yeah, really fancy knobs. But I mean, he
could go down to the point of, you know,
issuing decrees and, you know, making
that guy slip off his horse and doing
these little things in the midst of a
battle. And it was just the idea of it
is kind of what's uh inspired me through
the years to build these things. We're
nowhere near building turtles invention,
but uh
I I think to me that's kind of why I do
a lot of this. Um I'm going to start off
with an old program, Sim Earth, and go
through some of the elements.
[Music]
Let me change the monitor setting real
quick here.
Now, this project was a little bit
ambitious.
Um,
we were trying to do a simulation of the
planet.
Turn off the annoying music.
Uh, so you know, we started this
project. The intent of this project was
to kind of show how complex planetary
systems are,
show the linkages between various
systems that most people don't think
about. Most people uh up till recently
interdisciplinary study has been kind of
a a backwater thing and now it's getting
really in the forefront. But people have
been doing for instance climate models
or evolution models or biom models in
isolation without regard for the way
these things link together. So one of
our intents was to show the inter
relationship between these different
fields of study. Another was to give a
sense of the vast time scales over which
the planets evolved. Um and so our task
here was to kind of figure out what
would the interface to a planet be. The
uh the main window you see here is a map
of the planet we have. Um let me load
Earth. It'll give you a little bit more
sense of the scale here.
This is one of the scenarios you can
play with it. Earth modern day.
At this level, we're getting an overview
of the planet. Um, I can actually open
another window here. This is a local
window. This is what we use for uh the
local control of the planet. I can
actually use this to move that around as
a little finder for it. Um so in the
interface here one of the conceptual
things that we've done in most of our
products is that we have a distinction
here between the global in this window
and the local in this window.
That distinction also applies to the
controls and the displays that you get
from each window.
Uh on the illusion of reality whenever
you look at a map it's hard to imagine
that you're really seeing a real system.
So after playing with this for a while
in development um we started thinking
you know this is looks like a simulation
it doesn't look like a toy planet. How
do we make it look more like a toy
planet? So we went through a lot of uh
hoops and kind of came up with this
which is displaying the same data
actually in a more restrictive format
because you're only seeing half the
planet at one time. But uh in some ways
it gives you more the feeling of playing
with a planet. So this is my little toy
planet. This works the same. All the
maps that display on this work the same.
Uh this actually turned out to be the
appropriate place for us to show the
core because as you play the game the
model of the geosphere includes the core
coallesing which is changing the
continental drift rates and a few other
factors.
Um this really for the amount of effort
and time we spent on this I think was
more of a macho programmer thing. Uh
let's see if we can map this onto a
sphere in real time. uh a horrendous
amount of code and time and effort went
into that which probably was not worth
it. Um
but live and learn.
On the bottom here we have controls. Uh
I'll go through them very briefly. Uh
this is just the terrain basically.
Events show on this map. Um this is
continental drift rates. We can hold the
button down and get a view of the plate
boundary. what the plate names are. Uh,
on the continental drift in this game,
the continents are drifting around at
certain time scales and it actually
records the drift. So, I can come back
over here and replay the current
continental drift. This is an internal
record that it's keeping of the latest
continental drift. One of the inputs you
have in the program is creating
earthquakes, and you pick out which way
you want to push the plates. And, um,
kind of a high level of control in this
game.
This turns off the oceans so you can see
the ocean floor terrain. Uh we initially
had this just toggle on and off. We
found that by animating it um people got
a much better feel. It's not so much on
Earth because the continental plate
boundaries are so distinct, but on other
planets they got a much better feel by
actually animating the water going up
and down.
This is the uh ocean temperatures.
It's ocean currents, atmosphere,
rainfall,
air currents,
biome distribution. You'll notice for
each of these maps, there's a small key
that appears down here
showing you how to interpret the colors
or the vectors.
Now, one thing about this interface that
uh we later came back and looked at it
and kind of said it's so information
dense. Um, primarily when we were
designing this game many years ago, uh,
this was pretty much the standard screen
size, 640x 480. Um, since then, standard
screen size has gotten much bigger. At
that time, we were very concerned with
information density. How much could we
display without the user having to bring
up another window or uh, obscure what
they're seeing. So consequently, most of
our interfaces came out kind of like
these uh really fancy car stereoss with
the billion and a half buttons, you
know, and uh you know, if you're into
playing with buttons and all that in the
showroom floor, it's really fun to play
with, right? You know, it's got all
little buttons and modes and lights and
but then you're driving down the road
and you just want to hear music, okay?
So, you get totally lost with all the
buttons. Um
after finishing this program, I started
feeling that, you know, this was kind of
the fancy car stereo. Maybe we could
have been a little less dense on it. But
part of that again was pulled in by the
simulation design. You know, everything
in here is supporting the simulation and
what we were trying to do with that. So
perhaps that's as much a criticism of
the simulation as anything else.
So on that theme down here where the key
is to maximize what we can do in this
window, we have a toggle for that. Even
if we toggle it to this, what we're now
getting is a overtime graph of the map
that we're currently seeing up here. So
right now we're seeing the biome map up
here. And this is the uh current biomass
of the planet. Um I'm just starting the
model. So all these are coming up from
zero right now. This is the average air
temperature across the planet,
rainfall, etc. So the buttons up here
along the top basically are all data
output for the player. There are certain
things associated with each of these
fields that are global. And you can
double click for instance on this one
which is the biome map. And here you get
a global readout of the uh ratios of
biomes on the planet. This is like
grassland to forest to jungle to swamp
to desert. Um same with the other ones.
If this is the uh life form display,
diversity display. I double click on
that. I get global readings on the
different life forms on the planet.
So we've tried to collapse most of the
uh information that you can get from the
simulation on a global side up here on
the top row. Now on the bottom row, we
have these buttons. We have geosphere,
atmosphere, biosphere, uh, civilization.
These are the global inputs the player
has. So we have on the top here again
the outputs. The bottom here the inputs.
These are the factors that the player
can control. I can grab the axle tilt of
the earth and right here I can start
moving it around causing chaos. I can
bring up the meteorite impacts. I can
increase the continental drift rate. Um,
these are rather major uh, inputs for a
game, but it was kind of aiming high.
The, uh, one of the things that we've
tried pretty hard at, I think we've been
pretty successful at is keeping numbers
out of the user's face. So, whenever
possible, we do things graphically. So,
uh, just notice in here how few numbers
you see, but yet we're trying to display
a lot of information about the planet.
Now the local side we have the same kind
of things. Um
we have down here mostly the information
output except it's here it's mostly uh
organized as filters. So this is turning
off the ocean. This is turning off the
biome display, the city display.
These up here are the inputs. These are
new life forms I can drop down or
cities. Can put dinosaurs in North
America.
Um, I can raise and lower terrain with
this. Uh, I can just grab and move
things with this. I can move a dinosaur
to South America.
Um, these are events I can actually
drop. Uh, this is really where most of
the control to the player comes in the
game. Um, I can, you know, drop a
meteorite in the Atlantic
causing tidal waves and destruction.
I can pick out an earthquake and
change the uh vector of the plate
boundary.
So, these are the kind of things that
the player does in this game. Um, I want
to talk a little bit in each interface I
show you here about the help system
because our help systems have kind of
evolved over the years. We've tried and
tried and tried and we never can get
people to use them basically is what the
short story here. Um, in this one, the
shift key turns the icon into a help
icon. And any button or control you
click on
will come up with a description. Now, uh
I know this is really standard stuff
now, but this program was designed oh
about seven years ago. So, back then
there weren't that many established.
This is before balloon help. This is
before the little pop-up stuff and
windows and all that. So, we didn't
really have any established thing to uh
to go by there.
The uh down here you can see it's a very
confusing display which is why we put
all these in. What basically the users
ended up doing was turning off most of
the displays when they were trying to
deal with a certain problem and then uh
dealing with it on a local or global
level. Very rarely did they have all
these displays on. We can also turn on
overlay things like the heat rainfall
maps on top of this which uh makes it
even more confusing.
Now the time scales was one of the major
intents of this program. So I'm going to
start a new planet here.
This game actually runs at four time
scales. What we call the geologic, time
scale, evolution, civilized and
technology. We were trying to show how
the changes on the earth have
accelerated over time uh based on the
life primarily. So in this game, it runs
at the geological time scale until
you've evolved
multisellular life. And generally it's
going by a million years at a click and
then at some point you evolve
multisellular life and then it slows
down and it starts going by a few
hundred thousand years at a click. And
then once you've evolved intelligent
life, which is not necessarily mammals,
it could be radiates or reptiles or
whatever in this game. Uh it slows down
again. Each one of these is dealing with
different factors. uh the simulation
itself changes depending on what time
scale you're working at. We had a hard
time communicating this to the user
except through time. I mean they would
only really get the sense of this as
they played through the whole game. But
we did try to organize the the uh
interface to support this. For instance,
I can start a planet here. Starting a
random planet.
This is roughly when Earth began. It's
really redot. Uh we're getting a lot of
meteorite impacts. The continents are
drifting around. Um, the oceans will
form soon as the water condenses out of
the atmosphere, as the planet's cooling.
Um, down here at the bottom, the
information displays I showed you
before, we basically organize those
according to time scale. So, here we're
evolving very quickly. The kind of
events we're getting, meteorite impacts,
this is showing us uh tidal waves,
meteorites, major volcanic eruptions.
Um, continental drift map you can see is
changing very quickly here. So roughly
the icons on the bottom here are
organized from the things that occur
over the longest time scales on the left
to the things that occur over the
shortest time scales on the right. See
on the right here we have civilization.
So basically as the game is progressing
and you're advancing, if you start with
a a scratch planet like this, you're
trying to evolve life and promote it to
higher intelligence. Your focus will
actually be moving down this row. As you
move to the evolution time scale, the
climate model will get uh higher
fidelity and you'll start concerning
yourself with these factors. As life
evolves, you'll start concerning
yourself with the biomes and the life
forms. So basically what we were trying
to do here and maybe I'll get right now
a little bit oh before I do that let me
show you a few more windows because this
has a little bit to do with my u
postmortem.
Let me pause the model for a second.
other model other uh windows we have in
here. We have a history window which has
all the same factors collapsed on a
history graph.
We have reports which will give you a
report on the current state of the
planet based on your goals. And then we
have
our little guy window.
Now this this is our first stupid
attempt at an agent-based interface. Uh
we after we basically this this product
uh grew through recretion. Okay. Okay,
so we started with a simple little
climate model. Said, "Oh, that's cool.
Let's put in a continental drift model.
Oh, that's cool. Let's put in an
evolution model. Oh, that's cool. Let's
put in a civilization model." So, of
course, us as the designers, you know,
it made a lot of sense. We were layering
this model and it was building and
everything was resting on layers below
it and all made sense. But now, we
showed this to new users, you know, who
were looking to buy some quick
entertainment, right? And they look at
this and they start opening the windows
and all this and they were quite
overwhelmed. Um actually I got a paper
from somebody who was doing uh learning
studies and they they proved they were
actually doing some studies on group
learning. They proved that it took five
people to place ME Earth. One person
just couldn't you know divide up the
conceptual things and make the linkages.
So this is our our last ditch attempt at
trying to give some point source
collapse all the data into one score.
Give the user some sense of how they
were doing. Um this little face actually
kind of changes depending on how you're
doing it. Right now it's kind of uh in
an indeterminate state, but it'll be
really happy sometimes if the bios uh
biosphere is really thriving. Other
times it'll look really mad. You know,
we can come in and I can uh let's see.
Turn off the sun or something. It
doesn't like that.
Yeah, turn the sun off here.
Now we go to this display. Actually got
the biome display. Oh, just as we
evolved life, too.
So here the planet will freeze up now
really quick. Polar ice caps will crawl
down. You can see the uh air temperature
dropping precipitously on the graph down
here. These are the kind of problems
that we were trying to get the user to
face in this uh program. Uh in some of
like the evolution time scale frequently
you would get a runaway greenhouse
effect or
uh the planet would overheat and the
oceans would boil off which wasn't
really good for your civilizations. Um,
but on the postmortem for this one, you
know, I think we had too much window
clutter. Uh, we were trying to stretch
the user in too many conceptual
directions at once had we maybe uh cut
down the simulation to just include
climate or geosphere or a few other
things. I think we probably could have
gotten people to get deeper into it. But
probably the biggest failure of this had
to do with the failure mode itself. Um,
really if you're dealing with conflicts
and challenges in a game and problems to
solve, the whole game, the whole thing
is about failure. Really, you want the
game, the user to be failing
continuously in an entertaining way. The
user has to confront problems, fail at
them several times, but know why they
failed. Uh, generally when you play a
really good game, no matter what it is,
even if it's Doom or something like
that, you know, I went around this
corner, I got blasted. I know why I got
blasted. Next time I'm not going to go
around that corner so fast. I'm going to
sneak around the corner or go the other
way. It's really important that when the
user fails that they understand why they
failed so that they will go back to play
it again the next time and then fail
further down the line. In this program,
people were failing and they had no idea
why. You know, they'd be sitting here
playing the game and all a sudden the
plant would freeze up. And as designers
of the simulation, we had no idea why
either. This simulation was just, you
know, too complex and they had a lot of
chaotic kind of attractors in the
attraction space. And it was kind of
like you're rolling this marble through
this very flat space and every now and
then it falls into one of these chaotic
chaotic attractors and we can't really
say why. So really that was almost a
failure of the uh simulation design. The
game design just couldn't uh convey that
to the user. You know even with
constraints um we had a few things that
worked a little better. One of the
things we stuck in here I'll just show
you real quick is you can load Mars.
And so on Mars all you're trying to do
is terraform it. You have little things
you can drop in the environment on the
local level. Oops.
I can drop down um CO2 generators or I
can uh impact Mars with ice meteors.
If I do enough for those, I'll start
forming an ocean. Uh one of the other
tools we gave the player was a monolith,
which kind of increases the sentience of
the little creatures on the planet.
on the failure mode. Um, one thing I
just want to mention real briefly is
that, uh, I've seen two different
failure modes between kids and adults,
there seems to be a big difference. Um,
adults, primarily, ones that, uh, kind
of grew up before the computer
generation really got into full swing.
When they're put in front of a computer,
they're afraid of failure. Generally,
they're timid. They're
they're very uh, they think twice before
they click a button. They don't just try
anything. Whereas kids, they fail all
the time. You know, they kind of like
failure. You know, failure doesn't
bother them because they're always
failing. When you see a kid build a
tower of blocks, you know, they'll build
it and they'll knock it down. Oh, it's
fun. What's important for the kid is
that the failure mode is fun and
interesting. Okay. What kids don't like
is a boring failure mode. Adults are
uncomfortable with failure in general,
which is what makes kids so cool. You
know, they're just really fun to watch
them. And that's I think one of the
reasons they learn so fast. You know,
they're not afraid to fail and that
failure is really the basis of their
learning. Um, so when we show games to
this to kids, even something this
complex, it's surprising. I've had
eight, nine year olds playing this game
that knew everything about it, every
little control in there. They knew what
it did and how it worked because they
just went in there, you know, with both
guns blazing, pushing everything and
playing with it. And they had the uh
their interest level stayed up enough
and they didn't care that the planet
kept freezing up or boiling over. You
know, to them that was cool. To the
adults, they do it. The planet freezes
up and oh no, I can't play this. It's
too complex. And so they run away
screaming.
I'm going to skip to the next one really
quick, which is uh we decided that that
was a little bit too much for the user
to bite off. A little too complex, too
many windows. So um we kind of swung the
other extreme on this one. This is sim
ant.
Next one we decided we would instead
scale back our expectations a little bit
and just simulate an ant colony.
Once again, turn off the annoying music.
Now in this one again we have the
interface kind of broken out into uh
local and global areas. This is
primarily the local window. This is my
little ant. That little yellow ant
there. If I click in the window that my
little ant crawls around digs tunnels.
This is uh where most of the global
information is on this window. In this
game it's a little different. Instead of
having the tools on the side the tool
the primary tool in this game is the
ant. So most of what you do in this game
is by navigating this little ant around.
Now I just came out of the ground. Now
you'll notice something here. The uh
when you're outside the viewpoint is
straight down two-dimensional. When
you're in the nest, it's side view two
dimensional. We actually had plans at
the beginning of this for a very
elaborate three-dimensional display of
the nest and the way it really looks. We
did a few prototypes and most people
were just totally baffled. Just the 3D
navigation to them just totally confused
them. So we decided to fall back on the
experience of the users. We really
wanted the users to uh have direct
experience and be able to map this into
the real experience. So most users
experience of seeing an ant nest is in
an ant farm which is you know
two-dimensional basically side view like
this. Uh most people see ants on the
ground straight down like this. This
turned out to be no problem at all. Even
though you're going through this what
seemed at the time a major viewpoint
shift just by going out of the hole.
Most people didn't even notice the fact,
didn't even mention it. Um,
this ant can actually uh control other
ants to some degree. I can recruit ants.
I don't think I have too many. Let me
speed up the game a little bit here. In
this game, what you do is you crawl
around, look for food, feed your colony,
uh, establish food trails. Here's some
food over here. I can go pick up a
piece. Um,
bring it back to my queen. the uh in
some earth on the local window we had
scroll bars as this window has. But we
wanted to have the ant self-c centering.
Oh, we're starting to get a rainstorm
here.
That's what that blue stuff is. I have
it on pause.
So, here's how the user basically plays
this game as they go get food, establish
food trails, start fighting there. At
the other end of this piece of ground is
a red colony of ants. And so what you're
doing in this game is you're actually
battling the red ants for dominance.
Once you destroy the red ants, you win
this patch. Um so this is the local here
in this window. This is the global in
this window. We have in this game
actually kind of a meta game. So this
little area of ground here
represents about uh four square feet of
ground.
This actually is the whole game field.
So, this little blinking square on the
side here is the current patch of ground
we're in.
The uh object of the game here is to
actually start breeding new colonies and
starting take over the yard. And so, you
actually start spreading out as the red
ants are spreading out. At this point,
it becomes kind of a territorial game
like go. Uh, and the real reward in this
game is if you can get into the uh house
here. And so, you're trying to get the
ants to invade the house. and the the
highest food content areas like around
the fridge and sink and whatever. So,
this is kind of the strategic game
you're playing. Uh the tactical game is
down at the local level. Let me pop back
to the local level here. Um
in this game, we tried to keep the
failure modes after the Sim Earth
experience very direct and obvious. So,
if I'm crawling around and die, usually
I know why. So, in this case, I walk by
a spider and get slurped up. Um, now in
in today's multime media environment,
that would have been a 10-minute video
sequence, you know, with a but uh again,
this is way back. They shipped on like
one disc kind of a thing. Um,
so but we didn't want the emphasis in
the game design to be on not dying
because we really wanted to get the the
idea across that it doesn't really
matter if an ant dies. It's the colony
that matters. The ants are more like the
cells. The colony is more like the
organism. So, in the game design, we
were trying to support that idea by
basically making death free. When you
die, you just come back as another ant.
Your ant colonies lost one ant. That's
not a big issue. Um, on the map here, we
found that we were going back and forth
to this map a lot just to get an
overview of where we were. Uh, which
seemed kind of a waste. Generally, we
wanted to play this with full screen
mode like this. So, we put the map in
here as a little popup.
So, as you're playing the game, if you
just want to get a bearings on where you
are, if I want to move the screen
around, uh that's what that little map
is for. That evolved into the next uh
game we did, which I'll show you in a
little bit. One of the real issues we
had in the interface design on this one
was that we wanted to give the player
some global control over the colony
behavior. One of the things we wanted
them to control was how many ants were
foraging versus nest building versus uh
other things. Another thing we wanted
them to control was how many workers
were being uh born versus uh soldiers
and breeders. We had this elaborate
thing at first where we had like four
bar graphs and each one represented the
percentage of let's say workers. One was
workers, one was soldiers, one was
breeders. You'd grab one bar, pull it
up, the other two would go down. Uh or
you'd pull one down, the other two would
go up. It was very confusing to users.
We tried it another way with a pyraph
where you were pulling things and again
it was very confusing to users. What we
finally came up with was this triangular
control, which actually worked pretty
well. In this, you just move this thing
around and it's establishing a three-way
percentage. Um, in this case, it's
between the amount of different type
casts of ant that are bred in your nest.
If I want all breeders, I bring it to
this verticy. If I want all workers, I
bring it down here. So, I can establish
a three-way relationship actually pretty
quickly. And this is just through
testing. You know, we went through uh I
don't know how many prototypes to
discover this. Um, and then we have, of
course, you can do presets. So, we have
three presets. I might have one set for
fighting, one for making my nest bigger,
and that way I can go through those very
quickly. The uh, now the help system on
Sim Earth was the shift click. On this
one, we decided to make it a little more
basic. We just put little uh, question
marks in each window. If you hold down
the question mark, it basically shows
you all the icons. This is not unlike
kind of the current paradigm of the
pop-up contextsensitive help. We did
that in every window in the product. So
in this window we have the same thing
and in the map window we have the same
thing too.
The uh there are a couple things we did
experimentally in this game which I oh
just very briefly these are the global
displays. These are pheromone displays
you see from the ants. One of the main
things we were trying to communicate in
this product was why ants are so cool. I
mean ants are really really cool. You
have these little things that just
operate on these local rules and have no
idea what's going on, but yet when you
add them up, you get this surprisingly
intelligent colony. And this is really
what we were trying to communicate to
the user in this game. And that's why it
was important that they saw the
pherommones they were dropping because
we were actually trying to build the
behavior. We were actually building the
simulation fairly close to real rules of
ants. Um, as an example, there's a thing
that uh somebody did, I forgot his name,
he did in a simulation. And it was
interesting because it was one of the
few cases where the real behavior of an
organism was discovered through
simulation. And people always wondered
how ants were able to effectively sort
larvae at different stages. In other
words, they'll have one little room with
the uh little eggs that were just laid,
another room with the medium-sized
larvae, another room with almost fully
grown ones. These larvae at each stage
put out a particular odor. These ants
apparently, and he found this through
stimulation, have this very local rule,
which is to say if I'm walking around
with nothing in my mandibles and I come
across a larvae and I haven't smelled
its smell in my vicinity, I'll tend to
pick it up. On the other hand, if I'm
carrying a larvae and its smell matches
the area, the smell in the local area,
I'll put it down. Now in simulation you
can just scatter these larvae all over
the screen. Turn this rule on and the
ants will eventually you know pick up
the larvae that are sitting by
themselves walk around with them
randomly until they get to an area with
similar larvae and drop them and thereby
sort them very efficiently. So this is
the kind of thing we were trying to
build the simulation out of. Now we
didn't want to start the user at this
level with you know the mechanisms
through which this emergent behavior
occurs in an ant colony. We wanted to
get them into the game first very
quickly. You know here's how you play
the game. Here's how you walk around,
get food. Here's how you uh defeat the
red ants. So, what we were hoping and
was somewhat successful is that we
embedded in this in the uh we put in
this little infos.
And this is kind of like a little
hypercard oops
database about ants and ant behavior. Uh
so, for instance, these are just little
hot buttons. I can click on them. They
have pop-up definitions. Uh, and I can
kind of explore this at my leisure and
find out more about ants. A lot of the
information contained in here relates
directly to the game and the game play.
Um, we have sections in here that
actually go into that. So, I can back
up. I can go to the Oops, I've been
eaten.
You die a lot in this game, but it's
okay.
So, uh, this is actually a small
flowchart of the simulation in the game.
Oops. It gets stepped onto.
So, this is a very simple flowchart,
much simpler than the real simulation,
but we were trying to give the user the
information and have the user pull the
information out of the system rather
than in most educational products, it's
kind of, you know, present the user
with, you know, gobs of information.
Here, remember this, this is cool. You
know, don't doesn't matter why, just
trust us. It's cool. We wanted the users
to more play this for a while and start
wondering about it and say, hey, that's
kind of cool. I wish I knew more about
this. And then pull the information out
of the system. So this was you know I
would say reasonably uh successful in
the game. Another kind of experimental
thing we did in this
was u this blank icon here which we
called the mystery button. Uh what this
does this does something totally random
and unexpected every time you click on
it. Uh sometimes it'll tell you a joke.
Uh
sometimes it'll play the entire sound
list. Sometimes it'll, you know, wipe
out the entire red ant colony. Sometimes
it will give you uh 500 more ants in the
black ant colony or it'll fill the world
with food. We have about 50 random
things it does. Um we found this
particularly appealed to kids. Kids
really like this idea of, you know,
they've played with something, played
with something, they've gone through a
goal- directed state and all a sudden
they want to get crazy. This is kind of
the let's get crazy button. You know,
let's do something totally
unpredictable. Um but again, as in most
cases, the adults didn't quite uh relate
to it too well.
Now, on this product, I would say
I was we were actually our failure here
was more in the marketing side. We were
actually marketing this to a similar
audience that Sim City and Sim Earth
were market was marketed at. But what
this game really appealed to were the uh
10-year-olds. I mean, 10-year-old girls
and boys loved this game. Uh
20-year-olds and up thought it was too
simplistic. The model was too explicit.
Um especially when they failed, they
knew not only why they failed, but it
was too obvious how to solve it next
time. So, they generally only failed
once or twice. The game was too easy for
them. Um, the kids didn't mind that it
was too easy cuz the kids tended to
approach this more experimentally. Uh,
one of the features we put in the game
that again the kids seem to appreciate
more than the adults was experimental
mode. Now, in this mode here, I can
actually put down little things to play
with the ants. I can drop down little
walls. So, I can, you know, make mazes
for my ants and see if they can figure
their way out of them with their
pherommones. Um, I can add food.
I can feed some ants over here, kill
ones over there. I can, you know, put an
ant in the thing, feed him, and see if
he can find his way out with trails of
food to follow. Um, I can get
destructive. I can go spraying them with
insecticide.
Spider's pretty resistant. Red answer.
There we go.
The kids have played with this for a
long time. It was kind of amazing to me.
Um,
one of the other failure modes of this,
I think, was in the, uh, lack of
creative input. I mean, you had this
local control as an ant. You were
actually building up the colony, but
there wasn't a whole lot of creativity
really. Um, the ants would kind of build
their colony, you know, and you'd end up
with this kind of mish mash of a nest,
and the nest never looked like a
designer nest or anything. Uh, and it
was, as a game, you know, it was fine,
but, uh, it was a little different than
most of the products we did. I'm going
to go to another one now.
which is um our latest version of Sim
City or the one that was released a few
years ago.
Two six colors here.
Now, in Sim City, you're running a city
obviously um rather than ant colony
or a planet. Start a new city.
Now, in this one, we did a few things
different. Um,
rather than having the two windows, the
local global windows as in the other two
games, we decided to try and collapse
everything into one
into one window. And basically to do
that, we added zoom. So, this basically
for the most part is your map view of
this game. Um, I can zoom in and this is
pretty much the local view, but it
occurs in the same window. The, uh, let
me load a city.
There we go. Because of the uh,
isometric perspective we had here, we
had to add rotate buttons, which wasn't
too much of a problem for most people.
Um, got to be a little bit of a problem
on mapping some of the other data. The
uh
the centering tool
actually allows you to browse around the
city. I've always had a problem with
scroll bars. Um in Sim Earth, I first
noticed it, which is why we had the
little map thing as you drag it around
controls the uh local window. In Sim
Ant, we tried to address that with the
local ant that became the center point
of the window. In this one, we made a
special tool, the centering tool, which
just allows you to browse around from
any other tool. Also, I can hold down
the uh
oops, that's not the right key to hold
down the option key and go straight to
the centering tool. The uh now this like
Sim Earth was a pretty information dense
display. Uh at this point, we had kind
of changed our minds and gone to
floating pallets rather than uh an
integrated window. So, you'll notice
this is the toolbar and it's a separate
pallet. It never goes behind. We have a
lot of other windows that occur in this
that can be opened, but they're all done
as floating pallets because we basically
wanted the user to just bring them up
when they needed them and close them
when they didn't. And that seemed to
work pretty well. Actually, I was kind
of surprised. The uh another thing we
did different was that we tried to
collapse as much information as possible
into this main window. Rather than
having all these hundreds of different
display modes, we basically tried to
make everything graphic, but in a way to
where it kind of made sense. It matched
reality. There was a, you know, obvious
mapping here. So, just by looking at
this map,
pause you for a second. Just looking at
this map here, the uh user can get a
sense of a lot of the data that's
actually going on. I can see the density
of development, the population density.
I can look at the current zoning at each
of these lots. If you look very closely,
there's a little color-coded thing on
the border. the uh of course where the
roads and buildings and terrain are. I
can see the traffic levels. Um I can see
the power status if power goes out to a
certain area. The uh toolbar over here
is organized into roughly four areas.
This top area up here are the tools in
the game. These are the inputs that the
user is able to uh have to the
simulation. This is a bulldozer. So I
can level terrain of a bulldozer.
This is uh a road. So
each tool is basically one of three
types. There's a uh basically a point
select which is like drop a tree
or drop water.
There's a line select which is the road.
And then there's an area select which
would be the zones. That's like a
residential zone or commercial zone is
an area select. Each one of those works
you know as a single click also. So the
user doesn't have to worry about what
mode they're in. They all if they just
want to single click each one that works
fine too. Um
one of the things this was actually this
is a sequel to the original Sim City
that we did many years beforehand. One
of the things we did in the interface
the interface is much more complex but
we tried to organize these tools
actually in the same order and using
similar icons to the old Sim City. So
people who have played Sim City before
can come into this and they know the
bulldozer is going to be the top icon
and the road is going to be next to the
uh rail. The additional detail that we
added in this basically we did in pop-up
menus. So whereas Sim City had a road,
this one has um five different types.
Whereas Sim City had one type of
residential zone, this has two. This has
many different bulldozer modes.
Basically, if a user just boots this up,
doesn't read the manual, which is what
they always do, they just click on the
buttons and they work kind of like they
expect them to. As they start playing
with it a while, they start realizing
that each of these has a pop-up menu.
Some of them bring up dialogues. Uh and
that's where they can start learning the
program. There's nice early I mean nice
easy learning ramp built into the
program.
These things around here are basically
display functions. Uh the rotate world,
zoom in, zoom out, centering tool. This
sign function allows
the user to put new signs in the city.
Now, these are kind of important a
little later on because they're used in
the newspaper when an event happens. Uh
you can sit there and name all the
different districts of your city. You
can also name the different buildings.
And again, we're trying to prop up the
illusion of a real city. A, we're also
trying to get the user to care about the
city. Now, the city thing seems to work
better than, for instance, the ant
colony or the planet because the user
actually has a lot more creative control
over the system that they're dealing
with. When I do something in Sim Earth,
you know, no matter what I do, it's
going to be erased in a billion years of
erosion. Uh, in Sim City, I build a road
and it stays there most of the time as
long as I fund it and repair it after
fires and whatnot. There's a lot more
permanence to Sim City. So, as a
consequence, after I've been playing the
game a while, what I've got on the
screen is something very much that I've
created. You know, I've built a model of
a city as a player. In Summer Earth,
I've done the same thing,
but the changes I made just are not
permanent. The bottom level down here
are uh additional windows or actually
pallets I can bring up. This is a uh the
map which again here we're pretty much
have replaced with the zoom out level of
this window. But this little map allows
us to bring up the data layers. So for
instance, I can show uh the crime and it
will be mapped onto this map over here.
We actually originally designed this
little map as a diamond shape to match
the orientation of that. Users found
that totally confusing. Um we changed it
to this. it was still confusing because
the user had to make basically a 45
degree rotation in their mind between
what they're seeing on this map and what
they're seeing on that map. Um, we
almost took it out altogether and just
left it as the uh selection icon, but uh
for some reason we didn't. I don't
remember why. Um, but most people never
You could also grow this and use this as
your primary map if you wanted to. Some
people felt more comfortable with this
map, but not many. Most people brought
this up, used it basically just for the
icons on the side. to uh apply to the
bigger map and you can zoom in and use
the same controls and get a detailed
area. I can actually toggle between so I
can look at where the highest crime
areas are in relation to the buildings
and structures there. Um these are
graphs, boring graphs. These are uh
population cohort graphs. In this model,
what you do over time is uh in a lot of
ways represented here in terms of to
bring certain industries into my city.
There's actually a national economic
model in the game. So around the turn of
the century, steel is a big national
demand industry. So are textiles.
Prochemical kicks in around uh the 50s.
Uh media electronics kick in a little
bit later. So if you want your city to
grow on the industrial base, you
actually have to have the right kind of
uh labor force. So for instance, if I
want to get heavily into electronics, I
have to have a pretty high education
level. This is the education level
currently in my city broken down by age
grouping. Um I address this actually by
building schools, museums, libraries.
Each one of those buildings applies to a
different uh age range on this bar
graph. If I build primary schools, it's
going to boost the bars on the 0ero to
10 year old range. Over time, these bars
obviously scroll to the side. The area
between 20 years old and 55 years old is
considered the workforce. That's
averaged into this EQ here. that average
is going to affect these uh industrial
how many of these industries will come
into your city and how fastly how fast.
So this is the kind of problem we were
trying to get the user to confront in
this game. Long-term planning issues
like in Sim Earth on the very bottom
here. So, we've gone through the tools
up here, display items there, additional
windows and clutter there, and the
bottom
we have filters. This uh information
here, information window here was too
complex for certain uh tactical things
that the users were trying to do. So,
these basically allow the user to turn
off parts of the data that are being
seen.
I might just want to see the terrain or
just the road network in isolation. Um,
another major part of this game uh
requires that you build underground
infrastructure. This shows you the
underground infrastructure in the city
where you're building subways, water
manes, and such.
The uh now like like the Gaia and Sim
Earth, we were trying to find a way to
collapse information here to give the
user a very quick thumbnail on how they
were doing. And so we spent a lot of
time building this with limited success.
Um, what this is, it's the newspaper
that you can get in your city. As your
city gets larger, you can actually
subscribe to different newspapers. Each
one has a different slant on the news, a
different layout. Um, but most of what
you see in the newspaper actually is an
output from the simulation model. Uh,
you can actually click on the articles
and it kind of randomly generates an
article trying to randomly describing a
real problem. Um
they also describe uh the current things
that the uh residents are having
problems with. You know like this one
for instance this article is telling us
that we need more power having too many
brownouts. Um this is giving us a sense
of the weather weather model which has
certain inputs. This uh some of the
papers have editorial sections where
basically it's a critique of you and
talking about the major problems you
have to deal with. So right now
education is probably a major problem.
it's probably high on the list of
problems that are bubbling up in the
thing. So, this in essence is another
type of data filter. We're trying to
take all the data maps inside of the
city, collapse them down into a in a way
that most people are familiar with. Most
people find out about the problems in
their city by reading the newspaper. Um,
I only wish that the technology
would have been a lot better so that we
could have made the newspaper much more
interesting to read. What this actually
was was kind of a Mad Libs thing where
we had hundreds of articles like a power
shortage article and we replace strings
like the people and place names and some
adjectives to give it some random uh
most people burned out on this after
about oh two weeks. You know, they'd
read it for two weeks, then they'd play
the game without it entirely. So, it was
kind of limited there. Um,
one of the things I noticed when we were
working on the original Sim City, we had
basically you build the city. We had all
these tools. We had bulldozer, uh,
roads, zones. I show it to people and
said, "Look, here you can build the
city. It's really cool." The first thing
they would do is they would find the
bulldozer because it was the first tool
and they'd try it, you know,
and generally it'd blow something up,
you know, you'd be bulldozing a building
and they'd say, "Hey, that's cool." And
then they'd start attacking the city
with a bulldozer like this.
And so they would sit there. It was kind
of like poking an ant colony with a
stick to see what happens. They had to
perturb the system to get a sense of,
you know, is it fragile or not? Or is
this a painting or is it really a
simulation? So it was like they were
testing the validity validity of the
simulation by poking at it and watching
it break. Um, and this is almost
universal kids and adults. Uh, and this
is just with a bulldozer. So we decided
to name that the Calvin syndrome. you
know, these people wanted to go in and
cause, you know, wreck havoc on these
things, especially if they didn't build
it. You know, the these are cities I
built and I labored over for hours and
hours. Look at my beautiful city. Oh,
I'll destroy it for you. And so, that's
when we put in the disaster menu. Um, so
in this one, you know, one of the things
a lot of people like to do is they'll
spend hours building up a city and then
kind of like the uh semant random mode
or experimental mode, except in this
case, I can, you know, bring some
disaster on my city. I can call in a
tornado
um or an earthquake
or a monster or everything all at once.
Usually, you know, these are fairly
major. They destroy the city, but people
just kind of like seeing the thing go
down in ruins. It's like, you know, uh I
guess Nero and the fiddle or whatever.
The uh
we did this in the original Sim City. We
kind of expanded on it in this one. We
uh one of the things you can do before
you get into the really full-blown plan
out the city in every little detail is
that you can play scenarios um which are
pre-built cities with certain disasters
or problems that you have to solve. Um
this is one of the ones I did that I
like because uh my home burned down in
Oakland Hills fire several years ago and
that was about uh a little about a year
and a half before we released this. So I
decided I'd put in the Oakland Hills
scenario and I put in my house. This is
my house up here on the hill. That's
where it really was. But now I can play
the game and I can go and I can dispatch
all the firefighters to save my house
and let the rest of Oakland burn down.
But uh
so at this level, Sim City becomes very
tactical. Um the time scale actually
freezes to real time for the most part.
Uh the uh
it's really funny the disaster thing
because I think people have to see how
fragile a system is before they really
appreciate
um building it. When people would
destroy the cities after I showed it to
them, they'd burn out on that usually
after about half an hour. They'd, you
know, blow them up, burn them down, hit
them with an earthquake. Then they'd
start rebuilding the city and they'd
start realizing how much more
interesting that was. It's almost like
they had to get the destruction out of
their system first before they
appreciated, you know, that part. And
then once they started building the
city, they had invested so much time in
building it. Some people would spend 10,
20 hours building one city that they
really empathized with it. You know,
then when the uh when the earthquake hit
randomly, you know, because they do
happen randomly also, they would say,
you know, oh, I've been hit by an
earthquake, you know, they wouldn't say
my my city's been hit by an earthquake.
They'd really identify and say, I've
been hit by the earthquake. Um
on this side we I think we did a pretty
good job whereas the sim earth was uh
too hard too complex very difficult for
the users to understand the conceptual
mapping of the simulation and sim ant
was too easy. Um this was kind of the
just right in terms of what I think the
uh complexity of the simulation turned
out and the visualization of it. Not
doing too good saving my house here but
uh the uh the only real criticism we got
from this was more from the educational
side. A lot of people, a lot of
educators use these in schools primarily
uh K through 12. And most of the
educators wanted in this game the model
to be more explicit. They wanted to know
the algorithms for why crime happens,
what causes traffic, what causes
pollution. Um
and perhaps, you know, it really it
needs a different design. I'm thinking
that, you know, we were really focusing
here on maintaining the illusion of
reality with things like the newspapers
and collapsing all the data into one
display. And in some sense uh that
requires almost a more structural view
of the system more like Sim Earth had.
Uh so this is again one of these things
where you have these two things in
opposition. Uh
this is most of what I wanted to show
you. Um I'd like to open it up just to
questions and get a little more
interactive at this point. Uh
teaches those things that are missing
from
models that are
Oh,
can you tell me about courseware that
people have developed that teach those
things that the educators want to know
about?
Yeah. Um you're talking about uh I
assume like hard copy as opposed to in
software. Yeah. Well, we have for each
one of our products, we have what's
called a teacher edition and we have
lesson manuals for each one which
generally try to take the programs
through bite-sized chunks, usually
something that can be accomplished in a
30-inut time period. So, they students
might concentrate on mapping in one time
period or traffic in another time
period. And then it would be related to
a social studies course. One of the
difficulties that educators have had
with these products is that we've
primarily been going at these with an
interdisciplinary approach. Um and so
there's not always an appropriate
classroom to teach these subjects in. It
usually gets lumped into either the
computer science curriculum or social
studies or in some cases earth science
is becoming you know lower and lower
grade levels and sim is a little more
but nobody takes ant behavior you know
even though there a lot of valuable
lessons to be learned there but uh
that's kind of the other one of the
other hurdles I think we're hitting in
the education but you know it is being
used.
Other questions? Yeah,
you talked a couple times about trying
things out on groups before you put it
into the final um final design that you
released. How did you structure those
trials? Who did you use? What kinds of
things did you do? What did you watch
for?
Very very informally and we've tried a
lot of things. Um as we've gotten bigger
and we have some money in the bank, we
can do real focus groups now. Um, we've
started doing that both uh toward the
end of a product to get a sense of how
users would view this, but also at the
beginning of the product before we've
done any code development and presenting
them with concepts and artist sketches.
Um, we've avoided, I think, some costly
blenders that way. But most of what we
do, and I'd say the most value comes
from informal testing, showing new
people. Uh, I've got a nine-year-old
daughter. I show her all the time. Her
friends come in, I show them, I show it
to adults. To me, I kind of look at the
uh the spectrum between kids and adults,
how they relate to it. And so, in some
sense, we're targeting the demographic
with these products. And we found that,
you know, we kind of learned that lesson
on Sim Ant that we might have had a
really fun game, but if we target the
wrong demographic, uh commercially, it
might not be the success it could be. Um
or we might have taken different design
paths had we known what the real
demographic was. So, one of the things
we try to identify early is the
demographic we're targeting. And then we
get into gameplay issues and the
interface issues in terms of what
confuses somebody that seems to be a lot
easier. I can show that to somebody in
our accounting department who doesn't
even like games and you know I can spend
10 minutes and if I can't get them to
figure it out I know there's a problem.
Um generally the kids will sit there and
they'll figure it out through trial and
error. You know they have the patience
and they kind of enjoy the failure but
uh the adults really are a good test for
that you know.
Yeah.
you.
Hi. Um, hi.
So, you use you say we here and I guess
I'm interested in a little more about,
you know, how you work with your various
colleagues, you know, how you set up the
group. Do you have an ant expert? You
know what,
you know, what what's the team like?
Well, generally on all these products,
I've done the research because that's
the part I really enjoy. Um, it's
evolved over time. you know, the the
kind of projects I'm doing now involve
bigger teams. Uh I'm doing very little
if any coding. Um on the current
projects I'm working on, I'm usually
doing conceptual coding or working out
simulator tricks, things like that. Uh
on most of these projects I've shown
you, I wrote about half the code in the
product. So I was heavily involved in
all the details. I'm still trying to be
involved on the design side. Um on these
projects, each one of these I shown you,
Sim Earth, Sim Ant, and Sim City, it was
me and one other person in a very close
collaboration. um with Sim Earth and Sim
City, it was the same person uh for both
those projects. Um most of it really was
through discussion with the other
person. You know, I'd come up with an
idea, he'd tell me what a terrible idea
it was, he'd come up with an idea, we'd
end up with some compromise in between,
and that was pretty well targeted toward
the final solution, except in a couple
cases. If we couldn't figure it out
between ourselves, and it wasn't an
obvious um solution, that's when we
would start showing it to people. We'd
both kind of broaden the discussion with
more people. Um, that process is
evolving as these games get more
complex. The current games we're working
on are far more complex than what I've
shown you today. Um, so now we're into a
design process that usually involves
three or four, five people, but
depending on whose project it is, there
has to be one person with the X on their
back that's going to call the shots. So,
you might have a group discussion over
is this icon blue or red or is this game
about ants or planets, but some person
has got to be pulling that thing
through. I've never seen a product
design through a committee that came out
well. You really have to have one
vision, I think, behind it. Um, and it's
really hard to communicate that vision.
I spend a lot of my time time trying to
do that. I have this idea in the back of
my head about why it would be so cool to
have a simulation of a thunderstorm and
what it would look like and what the
visuals would be like. And this is a
real example. I go around explaining
this to people and they stare at me with
a blank stare, you know, because I'm
seeing these things in my head, these
elaborate threedimensional displays and
these I kind of know what the simulation
would be and the kind of expected
emergent behavior coming out of the
system. I just cannot convey that to
somebody to the point where they're
going to drop a half million dollars on
it to develop a game. Um, luckily I'm in
the point where I can kind of push it
through and make it happen, you know,
just because they'll trust me on it. But
I think uh in our industry that's kind
of a really big issue. you have uh on
the financial side, people want control,
they want predictability, they don't
know what you're talking about, but you
really all have to have one person with
that idea all the way through from form
to style to mechanics to plumbing about
how to make that idea happen. So yeah,
who are your customers? What are they
like? And I'm talking about the people
who buy the product initially and then
also the ones who are repeat or um
really committed users. I'm thinking of
demographics and also other
characteristics of these customers.
Well, obviously it varies by product. We
have other products that I haven't shown
today which are more kid-based. We have
Sim Town which is kind of like Sim City.
Yeah, I'm thinking say for the Sim Sim
City 2000 that we just
like the kind of things I've shown
today. Generally, our demographic um
falls between about 20 and 35 or 40.
It's actually surprisingly old for
computer games. Uh when we do focus
groups um we'll invite people who are
registered customers. So we recently had
a focus group for the next version of
Sim City, the next generation we're
working on and we pulled kind of a
random sampling of Sim City 2000
customers. The age ranges were
surprisingly high. I mean there were
some people in there that were 60 65
years old that were avid gamers which
kind of surprised me. There's uh in the
game field basically there almost three
major areas. There's kind of the kids
early education market and that's
primarily the purchase decision there is
adult-based. I mean the parent based.
The parent decides, oh, you know, little
Tommy should learn math. I'll buy him
Math Blaster or, you know, I want uh
Susie to learn how to read. I'll buy
this. Then you get into from about the
10 or 12 to 16, it's kind of what we
call Nintendo Gulch. Okay. This is the
cart machine territory. this is where
the kids are buying Nintendo, Sega,
Sony, all that stuff. They're driving
the purchase decision. You know, they
want, you know, Hacken Slash 3 and
they're the ones that'll actually spend
their money on Hacken Slash 3 in that
area. And then you have kind of the
adult hardcore gamer market. But across
that whole thing in kind of a broad thin
veneer is the PC gaming market, which we
actually have, you know, a lot of 8 10
year olds playing Sim City. you know,
either their parent bought it for them
or they wanted to buy it or they got it
from their friend or whatever. But, you
know, we also have the 15-year-olds who
aren't into the hacken slash that are
buying it and playing it.
Yeah. I guess I guess what I'm getting
at is what do you know about those that
rather you have a rather unusual or
different game?
Yeah. Sim City, what do you know about
them besides their age and their sex?
Oh, you mean how much information have
we collected on them?
Yeah. And what what really what
distinguishes the person who gets this
and uses it from another 65year-old or
30-year-old who isn't?
Oh, I see what you're saying. Well, um,
right now the computer game market is
still what I would call kind of the
hobbyist market. So, these are people
that, you know, in some sense have some
time on their hands, are willing to
devote it to a hobby, and they've
decided that hobby is computers. Um,
that's kind of what how our the PC
gaming industry has grown, which is a
very different model than from the
Nintendo industry. Nintendo industry has
gone in and decimated the model building
hobby toy industry is what it's done. Uh
but the people who buy this you we've
actually done a lot of things where we
ask them you know what kind of game what
other games do you have and we look at
the intersections between our games and
the other games and we haven't you know
come to any really firm conclusions
actually if anything our games have a
much broader I think demographic than
most games. We tend to have a lot of
players who only play two or three games
and this is one of them or these kind of
games are the only games that appeal to
them and it's just the fact that there
aren't more of them out there that keeps
them from becoming a hardcore gamer. So,
uh, and we get a lot of kids like that,
too, who, you know, maybe don't play
that many PC games, but they'll play Sim
Ant because they think it's cool because
their parents gave it to them, maybe. I
don't know.
Yeah.
Uh, what projects are you working on
now? And, uh, if you don't if you'd
rather not talk about that, uh, what
projects or models uh, had you
considered before that were kind of
interesting, but you didn't do?
You mean like system what systems have I
considered modeling?
Right.
Oh, god. and also what systems are you
currently working on if you if you could
talk about them.
Okay. Well, one thing we're working on
is a uh we've been kind of interested in
our company for a long time about the
idea of data portability. Um really let
me back up just a little bit here and
this might be a little bit more of an
answer than you were looking for, but uh
most of the game industry right now is
built on kind of the movie model. So you
spend a lot of money developing one big
title. You come out with it. You
advertise it. It either, you know, goes
or it dies. And then you do the next one
separate. Except, you know, for sequels.
There's the one consistent genre that
does better than any other genre in the
game industry is sequels. Um,
now what we've tried to do and we're
kind of working on slowly over time is
to build our games more as a hobby model
where people buy and collect things, but
they relate to the last things they
collected. You know, it's like a train
set. you build this train set and
people, some people get into the
building the hills and the cliffs and
the mountains and the trees really
detailed. They could care less about the
train. Other people get into the village
or the track switching and the
scheduling. Everybody can kind of come
into that, take their particular slant
on it, their interest, and focus in that
area in great detail. Um, I'd like to
see the game industry kind of evolve
that way. And part of that is I want the
games to actually be able to uh have
persistent data that can move from one
game to another or have a large data set
that I can reuse in different ways. Um,
let me show you something real quick
here, which is kind of along those
lines. Just this is just a kind of a
little This is one of the things I'm
working on, by the way, but it's uh
it'll give you some sense of what I'm
talking about. Um,
this is a game I call Dollhouse.
And if this looks familiar, it's because
I've just loaded a Sim City file into
here. Okay, so what we're seeing is a
Sim City file. But now at this point, I
can actually zoom down to the street
level.
this zoom in here. This little area
right there by the street is what I'm
zooming into. I can keep zooming in and
now I can get a little person. This is
me. I'm actually controlling this person
with a puppet. I can wave and walk
around and do things. Um
I can actually walk anywhere in the city
here. Uh we haven't don't have a full
database in this, but I have a database
for all the roads and the terrain. Um,
it's very feasible for us to put a
database in for every building in Sim
City so that I could actually walk
anywhere in the city I've created and uh
into any building. And so the tools in
this game are more architectural tools.
So uh I can let's see real quickly. I'll
build a foundation here. Oops. Yeah,
there we go. Um this is a wall tool. I
have different wall styles.
So, what we're trying to do here is
designing kind of like a little CAD
program that a a 10-year-old could use,
for instance. So, very simple tools,
kind of like you would build a little
dollhouse. Um,
so I just made a really quick little
quick and dirty architecture here. Um,
we also have landscaping tools. So, part
of this game is, you know, planning my
yard. Um, we've played around with some
L systems for generating the plants in
real time, which a little too slow,
actually.
So, these are windows. Um, I can zoom
into the house.
So, this right now is not much of a
defined game. Um, but this is almost
more of what I would consider a hobby. I
could take a city that I built in Sim
City and now I can come live in it. I
can actually, you know, stake a claim. I
can uh build my house and I can decorate
it and invite my friends over. We're
looking at actually having like a little
family model inside of here so that uh
there'll be little personality models
for these guys. there's behavior
embedded in some of these objects. So
the cool thing about this game is that
almost the entire simulation is data
driven at at a local level. Um so for
instance I click on an object. Um
now what's interesting here is that uh
that person in the person's data
structure there's no knowledge of any
objects in this environment whatsoever.
The object itself contains the
descriptions of how a person interacts
with it and why, what the animation
sequence would be and the scheduling. So
the this is my person. This is my little
avatar. I can also add uh pop in some
simulated people that'll walk around and
do things. Right now they they're kind
of ghosts because they don't know about
the walls, but uh they'll walk around,
they'll have conversations, some of them
will panhandle each other. Um
but what's cool is that uh the behavior
is entirely distributed in the
environment. So a person's in a room,
they have certain motivations, needs.
They might be hungry, sleepy, lonely,
angry. They scan the room for people and
objects. And the objects are all kind of
advertising, you know, if you're angry,
pick up me and throw me. If you're
hungry, eat me. You know, and
there's the communication there is all
data driven. And even the animation, so
the animation of these people is done
through this kind of component- driven
geometry. So they don't have to know how
to ride a bike or sit on the toilet. The
object tells them how to when they come
up and say, "Okay, you know, you're
gonna make me less hungry. I'm going to
interact with you. What do I do?" The
object tells it what to do. The cool
thing about this is that we can drop new
objects in later. You know, maybe it's
network based or maybe it's something
else. We can even have tools where the
users build these objects. Maybe one
person is totally into designing
furniture or designing exercise
equipment. I don't know what exercise
videos. But if we had a tool to where
the user could build these things, they
could then post them on the net and
other people could download them and
then the environment gets more rich. And
so to me, this is what I want to move
towards more of the hobbyist kind of a
thing, distributed environment, um, with
objects that can move from one game to
another. So this might be, you know, one
game I'm playing here. I can, this is
actually a very similar data structure
to Doom. I could be in here in a 3D
point of view, you know, shooting the
person on the toilet if I wanted to.
maybe as a different game player in a
different game, but still running off
the same server. So, you know, in a way,
you could think of this as a graphic mod
or something like that. But, uh
um what about from person to
Yeah, go ahead.
Finished.
Person to person. You talking about like
the information obtained that's
contained within the objects, but
it can be information I guess in a
person, another person that you would
want to interact with in the
environment. Did you have you looked at
any reasons why you would go want to do
that or
Oh yeah, that I mean that's that's the
hard problem.
I mean simulating ants is hard enough
when you get to people there's really no
hope but
they use
well yeah
there are two issues here. You can look
at this as a technology. It's not a
product right now. Um and there are
future directions this could go. I could
see this becoming, let's say, a
multiplayer
network mud kind of a thing. You might
have a thousand people playing Sim City
from the bottom up. Each person building
their own house in a big multi-user
space. In which case, that issue is a
little less important because most of
the people are real people and you're
dealing with puppets. As a standalone
game, which is probably our our closer
target, we have to deal with the problem
you're bringing up, which is how do we
deal with people to people? And it's
hard. I mean, there's just I'm sure
Terry can elaborate on that more than I
can. But you know, the best thing we can
do is prop up a convincing illusion. Uh
we don't have to be doing a valid
simulation of human personality. What we
have to do is we have to put up
something that's ambiguous enough to
where somebody can read in what they
want. Actually, in this thing, what I
have right now are people come up and
they converse, but you don't hear what
they're saying. They just gesture and
sometimes they look mad, sometimes they
kind of look contemplative. Um it's kind
of interesting. uh
how much people will read into that.
There's this kind of dynamic that we've
seen again and again where something
happens in Sim City and they said, "Oh,
I was running my nuclear reactor near
the red line and then there was so much
smoke coming out of it. This plane
crashed and because of that, this and
that happened." And they'll describe
this long causal chain of events that I
know does not exist. You know, I
designed the simulation. I know that
there's no linkage between the power
output of the power plant, the planes
crashing, but they're convinced it
exists.
They're using it as a medium for telling
stories, right? Making up the stories.
the micros here.
Yeah. They're using it as a medium to
tell stories about where they're, you
know,
using it as a piece of paper to write.
Yeah, that's exactly right. You know,
this is there's a parallel simulation
going on here in the game. Everybody's
taking a linear path through this and
they're basically most people will
attempt to understand things like this
with a story. You know, think about I
did this then that happened because of
that. And so the story becomes kind of
their logical connection, their logical
reverse engineering of the simulation
that they're playing inside of. Um,
now the uh on the people's side, I think
we can do a lot in this as a product by
propping up that illusion of people. You
know, again, if this is a dollhouse, uh,
we don't want the dolls to be sensient
things. We want the dolls to be
interesting enough to where I can play
games with them. Um, there was actually
a really interesting doll that this
company came out with. It was Oh, it was
a Worlds of Wonder. They had this really
cool doll. I've got a couple of them
after they went out of business. It's
called the Julie doll, but it was like
this $250 doll with voice recognition
and it said all these things. It had
just, you know, a huge amount of ROM
with digitized speech in it. And so, you
would sit there and try and have stupid
conversations with you. And really, it
was kind of Eliza, you know, where it
had keywords it would recognize and give
you these kind of uh non-committal
responses. But in the testing of that,
well, first of all, it was a $300 doll.
Who's going to buy their kid a $300
doll? So, it was really more It was
actually the only doll I've ever seen
that appealed to grown men. Grown men
love this. I mean, this is a hacker's
doll, but uh they put I talked to the
guy who was working on this project and
he said they put this in focus groups
with girls and they'd play with it for a
while and then after about a half an
hour they take the batteries out and
keep playing with it. And what was
happening is that the girls were
propping up this elaborate fantasy, you
know, in their play. And the dolls were
supposed to be a structure for that
fantasy. They weren't supposed to be the
fantasy. the doll was telling them what
the fantasy was and it was conflicting
with what the girls were saying and so
it was interfering actively with their
fantasy in their play. So in that
regard, I think we can actually kind of
take that path with these people and all
we have to do is deal with them on a
very local, you know, kind of a state
machine, Bradenberg machine kind of
level and say that they're angry and
they're hungry and they're sleepy and
then we can actually do some things
where maybe they have a little uh what
you might call structural ambiguity
about what they're actually saying. You
know, one of the thoughts I had about
this project in particular is that you'd
see the people go up and they talk and
there would be some tenor, some kind of
a a flavor to their conversation, but it
would be more like peanuts. The when
they did the PV the TV show of peanuts,
you'd hear the adults talking and adults
would always be
or, you know, soft or loud. You could
tell if they're mad or angry or what,
but you wouldn't hear what they were
saying. You'd have to read that into it.
So, uh, I think this is the area where
we sidestep the issue just because, you
know, as a commercial company, we have
to ship a game. We're not doing a
research project. So, that's a
long-winded answer. Sorry.
Yeah.
Um, if you do do that and you have um
people can read into what people are
actually doing in the game, um, more
that sort of interfere with their
expectations in the simulation, if the
simulation doesn't actually um, meet
those expectations, if they're reading
too much into it and it's not really
happening that way,
won't they be sort of misled in their
um,
expectation? It really comes down what
the simulation is. Um,
it's uh that I think would be addressed
on the game design side. Um,
again, I mean, just in terms of reality,
I don't think there's any way I'm going
to come anywhere close to simulating a
person. Um,
with a lot of tricks, I could have these
people walking through the day, getting
up, uh, taking a bath or a shower,
fixing breakfast, going to work, while
at the same time deciding that I'm
bored. I'm going to sit on the couch.
I'm going to turn on the TV. And
how you make that into a game design
might have a lot to do with how valid
the simulation of the people has to be.
You know, if it's a story kind of a game
where you want drama to unfold at the
right time and the conversation between
these two people is a crucial thing that
happens before he gets really upset and
does that then yes, the model would need
to be a real simulation. I really don't
think we're anywhere near that though. I
mean, uh, really, I think, you know,
unless you're in a very very tightly
confined domain, uh, you're going to
have a hard time dealing with this
open-ended simulation about people in
that way. So, uh, I I think really,
unfortunately, we're not there yet, and
I think it'll be quite a long time
before we are. So, really, we have to
constrain what the user is doing. You
know, maybe it's just a dollhouse. Maybe
all I do is I kind of, uh, I have to get
two people to meet at a party, and
everything else is kind of indeterminate
about what they say and all that, and
I'm moving furniture around. So there
are a lot of game design things we can
do with this without doing a personality
model.
So it's an AI game versus a multi-user
game would be easier to design than an
AI game.
So you're you're saying a multi-user
game would be easier to design than an
AI game because you could I think so
it's just the technology of
communicating and time lags.
This is how interest I mean you're
always building models of the system
you're playing with. It's easy to build
a model of a stupid computer agent. It's
hard to build a model of, you know, your
head while I'm talking to you. That's
what's interesting is trying to reverse
engineer your thought process.
Yeah. There's a lot of like commercial
services, worlds away and habitat things
that have been done that only have other
people. Yeah.
Robots or anything, and they're pretty
successful just because of that.
Yeah. People are pretty interesting.
I had a question related to that which
is the standard modes of game play are
individual and then competitive. There's
more than one person and it would seem
that your games are the most likely of
any to have a mode of multiplayer
cooperative play where you're working.
You mentioned five people playing Sim
Earth and trying to work together to
accomplish something. Does that happen
very much or pretty much when people are
playing with them it's one person?
Uh well yeah actually it happens a lot.
Um especially more with the kids than
the adults. um the kids and not just our
games but other games too. Uh one of the
interesting things I've noticed with my
daughter is that she almost never plays
computer games or video games by herself
but if a friend's over they'll both play
them and usually it's one of the
controls and the other one is the
backseat driver. And it's the dialogue
between the two that really makes the
game interesting. So really for them the
game is facilitating a social
interaction. Um and the game itself is
not interesting enough for them to
really spend much time with it. But in
terms of it facilitating a social
interaction, that's when uh it really is
valuable. And I think a lot of kids,
that's a big attraction of this Nintendo
Gulch thing is this peer group that's
out there. And they may have Super Mario
Brothers and I'm motivated to get better
at it and find the hidden level. So I
can tell Tommy and it's kind of like
social currency that I'm passing around
this knowledge I have about the system.
And then Tommy comes over to my house
and we play it together. So really in
some sense, I think that's kind of cool.
social interaction that these systems
involve in our games. Um,
it's it's much more e it's much easier
for players to do that in our games
because of the time scale involved. It's
not like Doom where I can't stop and
think and every second, you know, I'm
moving. It's not like driving a car. Our
games are more like, you know, sitting
back and taking a leisurely stroll. So,
I think the time scale probably has a
lot to do with that.
Yeah.
What sort of looking back to where you
were uh 10 or 15 years ago, what what
have been some of the surprises and how
things have gone?
Surprises in the industry or surprises
in uh
the working as a designer
in the industry and where where games
are and what direction that's they've
taken. I'm kind of surprised right now
that there seems to be a shift in some
sense away from deeper games and this
kind of happened with Doom and I've
played enough Doom myself that I can't
sit here and criticize Doom for not
being fun. It's a very different kind of
thing than Sim City. Um, right now
that's driving a lot of the industry.
Uh, related to that is the distribution
system, which I don't think you want to
hear about distribution because it's
extremely boring topic. Um, but that's
really changed a lot in our industry. I
think that's probably going to be the uh
biggest change we're going to see in our
industry over the next few years. Um as
all sudden gets interesting again and
hopefully we get into perhaps a
network-based distribution alternative
distribution system. I think that more
than anything else will have the biggest
impact on the kind of games that are
developed and the economies of
developing those games. Uh right now a
lot of things are filtered out in the
distribution process that are really
creative and really cool and you just
never see and nobody can afford to
develop because they won't get on the
shelf. Um so that's kind of a big
surprise is how quickly that's happening
this whole net thing but surprising
everybody. Uh on the technology side 3D
seems to be getting uh 3D immersive
stuff seems to actually have some
staying power which has surprised me. I
thought 3D was going to come and go as a
fad, but now I'm thinking, you know,
actually it's going to stay. Uh, and a
lot of that is just that people have
gotten so accustomed to immersive
environments through things like Doom or
some of the current crop of the uh game
consoles, the PlayStation, the new uh
Nintendo Ultra 64 that's coming out.
you're going to have a whole new
generation of kids that are kind of
going to be weaned, you know, you know,
grown up on this 3D paradigm, you know,
used to 3D interfaces, used to
navigating around the 3D space. And so I
think that's probably going to remain
with us. Um,
more questions?
We finished right on time. Just right on
time.